Finding Aid for Lawrence W. Jones papers 1952-2006. bulk 1984-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lawrence W. Jones papers 1952-2006, 1984-1989
Jones, Lawrence W. (Lawrence William)
1 oversize folders
12 linear feet
University of Michigan physicist, involved in effort to have Superconducting Super Collider located in Michigan. Papers include documentation of the state of Michigan's proposal for the SSC and some material related to his teaching and professional activities.
02138 Aa 2 Ac
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were received in two accessions, the most recent in May 2009(donor no. 6067 ).
The records are open for research.
Lawrence William Jones was born on November 16, 1925 in Evanston, Illinois. He received a B.S. (1948) and M.S. (1949) from Northwestern University and a Ph.D. from the University of California at Berkeley in 1952.
Jones spent his entire professional career on the faculty of the University of Michigan, joining the Department of Physics as an instructor in 1952. He was promoted to assistant professor in 1956, associate professor in 1960, and professor in 1963. He served as the chair of the department from 1982 to 1987. Upon his retirement in May 1998 he was named Professor Emeritus of Physics.
On sabbaticals and research leaves from the university, Jones held a position at the Midwestern Universities Research Association (MURA) from 1956 to 1957, and was a Ford Foundation Fellow (1961-1962) and Guggenheim Fellow (1965) at the European Laboratory for Particle Physics of the European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN) in Geneva, Switzerland. He also held visiting posts at a number of academic institutions including Westfield College of the University of London (1977), the Tata Institute for Fundamental Research in Bombay (1979), the University of Adelaide, the University of Sydney, and the University of Auckland (all in 1991).
Jones' research spanned the range of particle accelerator design, detector developments, cosmic ray research, and experiments at many proton accelerators. His detector contributions included development of the luminescent (scintillation) chamber, various optical spark chamber concepts, and the ionization calorimeter for hadron energy measurement. His accelerator experiments included hadron cross sections, elastic and inelastic scattering, particle production, dimuon production, prompt neutrino production and charm production by protons. His expertise in cosmic-ray and accelerator physics made him a highly sought-after collaborator.
Jones served on the High Energy Advisory Panel Subpanel on Cosmic Ray Physics from 1968 to 1969 and on various NASA advisory panels between 1970 and 1996. He has also served on the leadership bodies of the Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (Fermilab) and the Universities Research Association. Jones was a leader in the effort to bring the Department of Energy's Superconducting Super Collider (SSC) to the state of Michigan during the 1980s. He developed the initiative for a site proposal, served as technical advisor for the site proposal team and was a member of the governor's SSC Commission.
A major focus of Jones' research efforts from 1983 on was the large, multi-institutional high-energy physics experiment called L3. Based out of the CERN laboratory and headed by Nobel Prize Laureate (and U-M alumnus) Samuel C.C. Ting of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), L3 constructed and employs a large detector to study and measure particles. Jones and the Michigan team led the design, construction and installation of the hadron calorimeter for the experiment, and Jones also participated in the Cosmics subgroup.
Jones is the author or co-author of over 200 scientific papers in refereed journals and books, as well as nearly 200 contributions to published conference proceedings, and chaired or co-chaired the doctoral committees of 18 graduate students.
Jones and his wife Ruth were married in 1950. They have three children.
The Lawrence W. Jones Papers document Jones' professional activities as an experimental physicist throughout his career from 1952 through 2006, including major research interests as well as his participation in professional organizations and the administrative life of the University of Michigan. Jones' papers are arranged in five series: Superconducting Super Collider, Professional Activities, Correspondence, Research Logs, and Subject Files
Subjects:
Jones, Lawrence W. (Lawrence William), 1925-; Particle accelerators--Location--Michigan.; Superconducting super collider--Location--Michigan.; Physics.; Cosmic rays--Research.; Nuclear physics.; University of Michigan--Research.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Midwestern Universities Research Association.; Stockbridge (Mich.); Dundee (Mich.)
- Superconducting Super Collider
  The Superconducting Super Collider series (3.5 linear feet) consists of proposals, reports, correspondence, maps, and historical materials related to the effort to bring the Department of Energy's Superconducting Super Collider (SSC) to the state of Michigan during the 1980s. In October 1983 the United States Department of Energy (DOE) announced plans to develop a large accelerator to study high-energy physics to be located at a site to be determined in the United States. In 1984 Michigan initiated a tri-state investigation into potential host sites with Indiana and Ohio. This coalition later came apart and Ohio and Michigan decided to submit bids independently. Several sites in Michigan were considered, including Monroe and Lenawee counties, Dundee, and Stockbridge. Site proposals for Dundee and Stockbridge were submitted to the Department of Energy, but only the Stockbridge site was announced as one of the eight Best Qualified Sites (BQL) and selected to host a DOE site visit in May and June, 1988. Michigan's effort proved to be unsuccessful when Texas was announced as the chosen site in January 1989 (The project turned out to be plagued with controversy. After a investment of more than two billion dollars, the Superconducting Super Collider project was later terminated in late 1993 by order of Congress). Lawrence Jones was one of the major participants in the Michigan SSC effort, and the material in this series reflects all phases of the campaign, including correspondence with government officials, members of industry, and researchers, contact lists for the Michigan Commission, information and reports on the science and costs of the SSC, and the multi-volume site proposals for Dundee and Stockbridge. The series also includes promotional videotapes for the Stockbridge site and audio and videotapes of media appearances by Jones and other participants.
  - Air Activation 1987 (Box 1)
  - Audiotapes
    - "Dr. Jones," undated (Box 5)
    - "Jackson, Sen. Smith, Jones, Sinclair, Shively," April 23, 1988 (Box 5)
    - "Larry Jones on J. P. McCarthy's 'Focus,'" February 2, 1988 (Box 5)
    - "SSC-2 parts," undated (Box 5)
  - Cartoon, signed by Gov. James Blanchard 1988 (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1987, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC) 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Contacts 1984-1988 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1983-1989 (Box 1)
  - "House Concurrent Resolution No. 1: A Concurrent Resolution Honoring the Superconducting Super Collider Commission and Staff," January 11, 1989 (located in outsize folder) (Box 1)
  - Information on Site Selection Process for DOE's Super Collider, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Invitation for Site Proposals 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Jacobi-Brock 1988 (Box 1)
  - Maps undated (some located in outsize folder) (Box 1)
  - "Material Prepared for the State of Michigan Senate Energy Committee," 1987 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Superconducting Super Collider Commission Appointment Certificate June 23, 1989 (located in outsize folder) (Folder 1)
  - "Michigan Superconducting Super Collider Health and Environmental Safety Issues-Questions and Answers," 1988 (Box 1)
  - Physics 1983-1987 (Box 1)
  - Politics 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Poster undated (located in outsize folder) (Folder 1)
  - "Preliminary Report on Ground Motion Measurements for Michigan Superconducting Super Collider," 1987 (Box 1)
  - "Proceedings of the Meetings on the Superconducting Super Collider Between Representatives of Industry and High Energy Physics," 1985 (Box 1)
  - Proposal and Budget 1984-1992 (Box 1)
  - Radiation
    - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Report of the 1990 HEPAP Subpanel on Superconducting Super Collider Cost Estimate Oversight, 1990 (Box 1)
  - "Scope of Services to Prepare Two Site Proposals to Locate the Superconducting Super Collider in the State of Michigan," 1987 (Box 1)
  - "Site Evaluation-Superconducting Super Collider Indiana/Michigan/Ohio," 1985 (Box 2)
  - "Site-Specific Conceptual Design Executive Summary," 1990 (Box 2)
  - Sites 1987 (Box 2)
  - "Siting the Superconducting Super Collider in Michigan," 1989 (Box 2)
  - Siting the Superconducting Super Collider in Michigan. Supplementary Data Submitted to the Department of Energy by the State of Michigan. Dundee Site.
    - Site Proposal, 9 volumes (Box 2)
  - Siting the Superconducting Super Collider in Michigan. Supplementary Data Submitted to the Department of Energy by the State of Michigan. Stockbridge Site.
    - Site Proposal, 9 volumes (Box 2)
    - Supplements Submitted March 15, 1988 (Box 3)
      - Supplementary Data-Maps (Box 3)
      - ISP Appendix D (Box 3)
      - Attachment 1-General Supplementary Data (Box 3)
      - Attachment 2-Site Specific Supplementary Data (Box 3)
      - Attachment 3-Utility Data (Box 3)
    - Supplements Submitted March 31, 1988
      - Enclosures 1 and 2-Supplementary Data for BQL Sites (Box 3)
      - Enclosure 3-Supplementary Data for BQL Sites (Box 3)
  - "Southeast Michigan Superconducting Super Collider Feasibility Study and Preliminary Site Evaluation (Draft)," 1986 (Box 3)
  - Speaking Engagements and History 1985-1992 (Box 3)
  - Stockbridge Site Visit May 31-June 3, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Superconducting Super Collider Briefing Materials 1986 (Box 3)
  - "Superconducting Super Collider Needs Assessment Survey of Physicists," 1988 (Box 3)
  - Videotape Scripts 1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Videotapes
    - "Legislative Forum," July 30, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Stockbridge: On Target, undated, 13 minutes (Box 5)
    - Stockbridge: On Target, undated, 8 minutes (Box 5)
    - "SSC and HEP," undated (Box 5)
    - "SSC Overflight," undated (Box 5)
- Professional Activities
  The Professional Activities series (1.5 linear feet) consists of material related to Jones' research, teaching, and administrative duties, as well as professional correspondence. Of particular note are correspondence, proposals, and reports related to two projects in which Jones was involved, a proposal submitted to the National Science Foundation to build an ultra high energy cosmic ray physics facility near Denver, Colorado, and a campaign to construct an Atomic Energy Commission-funded 200 billion electron volt (BEV) proton accelerator in Northfield Township, Michigan. The series also contains syllabi and reading lists spanning from 1968 to 1997 for physics courses taught by Jones, and biographical information about Jones, including a curriculum vitae and an audiotape of remarks given by Martin Perl upon Jones' retirement.
  - Alumni 1983-1986 (Box 4)
  - Audiotapes
    - "'Focus' J.P. Hydrogen," 1973 (Box 5)
    - "History of Physics Roundtable," May 1985 (Box 5)
    - "Remarks by Martin Perl on the Occasion of the Retirement Dinner of Prof. Lawrence Jones," April 25, 1998 (Box 5)
  - Cosmic Ray Program
    - Proposal Correspondence 1966-1969 (Box 4)
    - Proposal 1967 (Box 4)
    - Appendix 1967 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Proposal 1970 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Proposal 1971 (Box 4)
    - "The History, Highlights, and Outcome of the Michigan-Wisconsin Echo Lake Cosmic Ray Program, 1965-1972," 1973 (Box 4)
    - Proposal 1971 (Box 4)
  - Courses
    - Concepts in 20th Century Physics (College Honors 252-001) 1997 (Box 4)
    - Elementary Particles (Physics 468) 1992 (Box 4)
    - Energy and Environment (Physics 250) 1989 (Box 4)
    - Intermediate Optics (Physics 402) 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - Intermediate Thermodynamics (Physics 406) 1979 (Box 4)
    - Introduction to Mechanics, Waves and Thermodynamics-Honors (Physics 160) 1994 (Box 4)
    - Introduction to Physics (Physics 103 and 104) 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Introductory Physics with Calculus (Physics 242) 1970 (Box 4)
    - Non-Calculus Elementary Physics (Physics 126) 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - Particle Beams, Accelerators and Detectors (Physics 458) 1968 (Box 4)
    - Physics of Music (Physics 288/489) 1991-1996 (Box 4)
    - Radioactivity (Physics 303) 1970 (Box 4)
  - Curriculum Vitae 2001 (Box 4)
  - Department of Physics Correspondence 1982-1996 (Box 4)
  - "Final Report-Cyclotron Laboratory," 1983 (Box 4)
  - Midwestern Universities Research Association (MURA)
    - General 1956-1957, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Michigan Working Group 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - Midwestern Universities Research Association (MURA)/Midwest Accelerator Conference (MAC)
    - General 1953-1955 (Box 4)
    - Notes 1953-1956, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings 1957-1983 (Box 5)
  - Professional Correspondence 1970-1998 (Box 5)
  - 200 BEV Proton Accelerator
    - General 1966 (Box 5)
    - Clippings 1965-1966 (Box 5)
    - Maps 1966 (Box 5)
    - Report of the National Academy of Sciences' Site Evaluation Committee 1966 (Box 5)
    - Report on Soil Investigation of Michigan Site No. 1 for the Proposed AEC Accelerator-Northfield Township 1966 (Box 5)
  - Terwilliger, Kent 1952-1989 (Box 5)
  - Universities Research Association (URA)-Annual Meeting of the Council of Presidents 1988-1998 (Box 5)
  - Videotape
    - "Physics at Michigan," 1985 (Box 5)
    - William L. Williams Memorial 1986-1988 (Box 5)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (5.0 linear feet) contains Jones' professional correspondence starting from the beginning of his career at the University of Michigan in 1952. In addition to the chronological series from 1952-2006, there are separate chronological runs of correspondence related to Jones' work on the Cosmic Rays Project, the NSF Elementary Particles Project, and the Echo Lake Project.
  Researchers should note that correspondence from 1982 to 1987, when Jones was chair of the Department of Physics, is found within the University of Michigan Department of Physics records at the Bentley Library.
  - Chronological
    - 1952 (Box 6)
    - 1953-1956 (Box 6)
    - 1958-1961 (Box 6)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 6)
    - August 1961-December 1963 (Box 6)
    - January 1965-July 1965 (Box 6)
    - July 1965-December 1965 (Box 6)
    - December 1965-June 1966 (Box 6)
    - July 1966-December 1966 (Box 7)
    - January 1967-December 1967 (Box 7)
    - 1968 (Box 7)
    - 1969 (Box 7)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 7)
    - 1972 (Box 7)
    - 1972 (Box 7)
    - 1973 (Box 7)
    - 1974 (Box 7)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 8)
    - 1978-1980 (Box 8)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 8)
    - 1986-1988 (Box 8)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 8)
    - 1993 (Box 8)
    - 1996-1998 (Box 9)
    - 1999-2000 (Box 9)
    - 2001-2002 (Box 9)
    - 2003-2004 (Box 9)
    - 2005-2006 (Box 9)
  - Topical
    - Cosmic Rays Project 1963-1966 (Box 9)
    - Cosmic Rays Project, May 1965-Dec 1968 (Box 9)
    - Cosmic Rays Project 1969 (Box 9)
    - NSF Elementary Particles Project 1970 (Box 9)
    - Echo Lake Project 1969-1970 (Box 9)
- Research Logs
  The Research Logs series (0.5 linear feet) consists of two ledger-size research logbooks, one of which (dated 1961) contains some of the thesis work of Jones' student Samuel C.C. Ting, who received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1976.
  - Research log, Large-angle scattering project, Sep 1961 (Box 10)
    (thesis work of subsequent Nobel laureate Samuel C.C. Ting)
  - Research log, Small-angle scattering project, Richard Y. Y. Lu undated (Box 10)
- Subject Files
  The Subject Files series (2.0 linear feet), consists of Jones' personal files by subject matter. Major categories include materials related to Jones' work on the Superconducting Super Collider (SSC); work on various University of Michigan committees; and records of the Universities Research Association, a consortium of research universities for which Jones served in several capacities.
  - CERN symposium in honor of Jones' retirement 1998 (Box 11)
    (poster and participant list located in outsize folder)
  - Detector for DO Area 1981 (Box 11)
  - Detector for DO Area 1982 (Box 11)
  - Detector for DO Area 1983 (Box 11)
  - DPF Collider Workshop 1983 (Box 11)
  - Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (FNAL)
    - Fermilab politics (Box 11)
    - Fermilab Proposals 1983 (Box 11)
    - FNAL (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory) Physics 1978 (Box 11)
    - FNAL Summary 1994 (Box 11)
  - Future Physics 1980 (Box 11)
  - G.K. O'Neill (Box 11)
  - Grants, etc. 1954-1963 (Box 11)
  - MURA Tech Notes 1966 (Box 11)
  - MURA Tech Notes 1967 (Box 11)
  - Office of Energy Research minutes 1979-1985 (Box 11)
  - Office of Naval Research (ONR) 1968-1970 (Box 11)
  - Superconducting Super Collider (SSC)
    - SSC Accelerator Workshop 1983 (Box 11)
    - SSC Consulting 1985 (Box 11)
    - SSC DOE 1984 (Box 11)
    - SSC Geometry, Tipped Ring (Box 11)
    - SSC Radiation (Box 11)
    - SSC Safety Review (PSAR), DOE 1987 (Box 11)
    - SSC Superconducting Toroids (Box 11)
  - Trilling Committee 1981 (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan (Box 12)
    - Academic Affairs 1978-1979 (Box 12)
    - College Priorities Report Rebuttals (Box 12)
    - Cosmic Ray Project Proposal to National Science Foundation (NSF) 1967 (Box 12)
    - College Priorities Committee (CPC) Correspondence (Box 12)
    - LSA correspondence 1972-1977 (Box 12)
    - LSA Natural Sciences Program Evaluations (Box 12)
    - LSA Program Evaluations Committee 1975 (Box 12)
    - Office of the Vice President for Research (OVPR), Rackham Deanship search 1984 (Box 12)
    - Overhead (Box 12)
    - Peter Steiner Correspondence 1982 (Box 12)
    - Senate Assembly Academic Affairs Advisory Committee (AAAC) Research incentives 1979 (Box 12)
    - University calendar 1978 (Box 12)
  - Universities Research Association (URA)
    - Correspondence 1982-1987 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence 1988-1998 (Box 12)
    - Memberships, Schedules (Box 12)
    - Minutes 1981 (Box 12)
    - President search (Box 12)
    - Records 1980-1986 (Box 12)
    - Records 1988-1998 (Box 12)
    - SSC Business 1987 (Box 12)
    - Visiting Committee Review (Box 12)
  - Westfield College (UK) and Sabbatical 1977 (Box 12)
  - W.J. Schafer Association (Box 12)
  - Woods Hole 1983 (Box 12)
Related Material
Correspondence relating to Jones' tenure as chairman of the Department of Physics along with documentation relating to the work of Jones with the international L3 project is contained in the University of Michigan Department of Physics record group also held at the Bentley Library. Records relating to the Midwestern Universities Research Association (MURA) are housed at the University of Minnesota university archives